Kerensa Johnson, I can see you, and Jamie Tuta.
Tena koutou. Welcome.
Just want to unmute
your
screen there.
And we've actually got you for 20 minutes this morning, but we'll hand over to
you for any opening comments or query-
Ka pai
... remarks.
Can you hear us?
Yes. Thank you.
Ka pai. E mihi ana ki a koe, e Te Tiamana.
Koutou, e te komiti whiriwhiri.
Ka nui ra o te mihi ki a koutou.
Nō reira, tena koutou. Nei ra matou o Te Here Anuku. So thank you all.
Thank you for
the opportunity to present to you all this morning.
Alongside myself as the chair of Te Here Anuku Trust,
I have fellow trustees, Kerensa Johnson and Jeremy Banks, and we
also have our legal counsel, Horiana
Owen-Easthope online.
What we thought, Chair, is that with just some brief introductory comments, and
probably the best use of time would be to take any questions that the committee
might have.
And as you expect, we support this bill in its entirety,
and we urge that it be passed before the 2026 general
election, and that's consistent with the Crown's commitment under the
resolution
agreement that was signed in December.
And I think just for context, as the committee will know, this bill is not about
taking something from the public.
It is about finally returning trust land to its
rightful trust while preserving public access, conservation
outcomes, and practical relationships with agencies and
communities where it has been agreed.
In such places as Abel Tasman,
these arrangements have been agreed,
and we believe are generous, balanced, and firmly in the public interest as
well as in the interests of Ngā Uri being the
beneficiaries of Te Here Anuku.
But when we reflect on this particular kaupapa, it is
about whenua, and it is about whakapapa.
It's about our relationship and connection to place and to
each other.
And at the heart of this particular kaupapa is about restoring a
trust that has existed since 1845 but
was not properly recognized or managed by the Crown.
And so our tupuna have never given up on that promise,
and this bill
is the final legislative step to give practical effect to the resolution
reached after many years of litigation, negotiation,
and engagement. And I think with that opening, unless, Kerensa,
there's anything you want to add?
Chair, I think it'll be just most useful to
hand over for questions. But Kerensa, kei a koe?
Hi. Tena tatou katoa. Tenei te mihi nui ki a koutou
i te ata nei.
Kia ora, everybody. And just first of all, an apology.
Jeremy and I are stuck in transit as most people are today,
so it's a little bit noisy where we are. But we're here.
And just to add to what Jamie has said,
it's important just first of all, just to acknowledge our whanau who we know are
watching online.
We want to thank them all for their support, and we know that a number of them have
made submissions in support of the bill, and so just
acknowledge those of you who are watching with us
online. And also
to reiterate what Jamie has said.
Apologies. This is a really
significant
milestone for us, another, a step closer to the end of what's
been over 17 years of litigation in the
courts, hard-fought by the Crown.
But certainly the last few months have been incredibly proactive
and positive in terms of the bill that we have before
us, which we are very confident
about.
The bill doesn't attempt to solve every question with
respect to the trust estate,
and we've certainly done a lot of work over the last few months, meeting
with people in our community and on the ground, knowing that there
will be other matters that we will resolve together in the coming months and
years. So perhaps I'll leave it there, given I'm competing with Air
New Zealand, unless Jeremy wants to add just anything before we open
for questions.
I guess just a quick brief reflection.
Before we gathered for the first reading,
it was great to have the opportunity to end what has been a very
hard-fought process in a positive way, and so that's what we're really focused on
at the moment, is
what this enables for us, what this enables for our whanau, and what the future
looks like. So I'll just leave it there, open for questions. Kia ora koutou.
Thank you all for your
submissions and comments this morning. Really appreciate it.
Now we've got a question from Steve Abel.
Kia ora koutou.
Yeah, it feels like a somewhat momentous process, this one,
and long fought, and we acknowledge the many,
many years of effort and sacrifice that has gone into getting to this
point for you, for Te Here Anuku.
You express that you support the bill in
full.
What are the concerns that you have?
What are the things that you
look at
in the bill and that gives you some pause for thought,
that you would want us as a committee considering this
to take into account
as we consider it?
I think I'll provide some context and then maybe hand over to the team.
I think the bill-
Implements what was agreed in the resolution agreement.
Mm-hmm.
There are elements within the resolution agreement and also the bill
that, as Carenza noted, require us to work
alongside with others. And so whether that be the Tasman District
Council,
the Department of Conservation, and others.
So,
we couldn't prescribe everything.
And some might argue that prescription is something that we
should do, but it does require us to work
proactively and engage with
key parties that are utilizing our land for public
benefit and other uses. So I think there is a piece there that
in the spirit of what we've negotiated through the resolution agreement and
bill, requires all parties to come together in a spirit of
cooperation,
recognizing too the place of Te Here Angiku,
ownership of land, and responsibilities to our broader
beneficiaries. I think probably just the piece is
really around any sort of future
consenting.
There is significant change happening at the moment in terms
of resource management, and other reform programs.
But again, striking that balance that at a point in time should it
be the desire of future trustees and beneficiaries to
utilize land in a particular way, that there are those
mechanisms and that ability to be able to do that.
And so I think those are two elements.
Carenza, Huriana, anything else from you?
Thanks, Jamie. And to add to that, I would
say we do support the bill in its entirety.
We've worked really hard over the last few months since the resolution
agreement to make sure
we're very comfortable with where it has landed.
I think if anything, we
understand that through the select committee process,
we may
have the benefit of your thinking around any improvements to the bill.
But in terms of the material decisions
and the principles underpinning it,
we are very comfortable that they reflect the resolution agreement,
and the aspirations not only of Ngā Uri, but also of
course the Crown in terms of that ongoing
relationship.
Can I ask a sup on that, Mr. Chair?
Yep.
Yeah. Thank you very much for that.
One of the things that seems notable, I
suppose, is the extent of the obligation that
you carry to maintain those relationships with the other
interested parties, the Tasman District Council or DOC.
Should we have consideration of the burden that places on the trust,
in terms of resources, in terms of costs, in terms of
personnel?
And
obviously you've considered this and this is where it's got
to, but is there anything that we should be thinking of in that space,
or is
it as it's currently described, satisfactory in so far as there's enough
leeway for you to determine the terms of that
relationship?
I think, well, to start with, it goes to Carenza's point, right?
I think we've struck the right balance-
Yeah
...
given the time in which we've negotiated arrangements.
The bill and the resolution agreement does
rest on, as I said earlier, entering into positive relationships
with the likes of
Tasman District Council, the Department of Conservation.
On the Department of Conservation side, we've
taken some time to work through kaupapa or
relationship agreement, which considers things both at a
governance, but more importantly at an operational level around striking the right
balance between the responsibilities and
obligations of each party in relation to those lands.
And we'll be working through the same with the Tasman District Council and
a small part with the Nelson City Council around some of those areas that
are currently controlled and managed by them.
Thank you. We've got a question from Glen Bennett.
Thanks so much, and thanks for giving us your time this morning.
Really supportive of the process.
It feels like we're almost at the finish line, and there's been a
little bit of noise around this. How can you, I guess, reassure people
who are
asking questions about this, "Be not afraid.
This is a good step forward"?
Yeah. I guess, one, we've always encouraged and
invited others to understand the history and the context to this
particular issue.
The fact that this process is very much about
restoring land, that is land that always
belonged to the trust. And
it's righting a longstanding legal wrong.
And so I think that's the starting point.
In addition to that,
there has been
public commentary from
the Mayor of Nelson and others, and we can talk about this quite openly,
about alternative options in relation to trust
land for the Abel Tasman National Park.
And I think it's just important that you as a committee and I think the broader
public just recognize, I think, the balance that has been struck
by the trust, and the generosity
that the trust has shown to enable the arrangements for at least another
25 years for the park.
That, in our minds, is
a useful timeframe that enables us to sort of-
You know, work with the department and others over that period of
time. Current concessions continue with their terms, and
we've got quite a detailed statutory and operational
arrangements which I think strike the right balance
between providing public access, but also
recognizing the fact that
a portion of the park, and I say a portion, is now owned by the
trust. And so,
Karenza, anything else from you?
I think the history of this
issue is really important, which is, as Jamie talked about at the outset,
a private law trust established in 1845.
But the bigger rationale behind that was, it was always
about the shared prosperity of our families
and the people and community of Nelson.
So, the idea was that we would rise together
and create this community together.
And so for us as trustees, and I think as the
beneficiaries, that is a really important principle that has underpinned
all of the work we've done over the last
few years, and that will absolutely continue.
We know how loved all of our special places are at
home by all of us. We care about those places as
much as everybody else does, and we're not going anywhere.
So, we feel very confident,
comfortable that care will be taken with respect to all the
decisions that we have to make, and that we'll do that with our community.
And just thinking ahead to what you'll be
listening to through the course of the morning,
some of the matters that have been raised in other submissions are,
in our view, not appropriate for legislation or for the bill.
They will be addressed, as Jamie has said, through our
relationships.
Thank you. Dan Bidois.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. Kia ora, Jamie, and to you as well,
Karenza. This is actually just a supplementary on the previous question.
As you've correctly pointed out, there have been concerns raised with other
submissions around access and protection of
the park. So, I guess, in a nutshell, what would you say
to those that are concerned about future access and
protection of the coastal areas of the Abel
Tasman National Park? What do you say to those
particular people today?
Well, I think as
Karenza sort of just put it, people shouldn't be afraid.
And this is something that we've shared directly with the Mayor of Nelson,
former member of Parliament, is that we care deeply
about these places. I think
the generosity that has been shown by the trust is one where
we've developed a mechanism, and we have certainty in relation
to the Abel Tasman for the next 25 years,
to ensure that public access is maintained and that
special place is protected. People would say, "Well, actually,
what's going to happen once that 25-year period sort of ends?"
And the message that we've given to everyone is
we've got time to work through what the opportunities might
be
for that special place, and that's something that we'll
continue to discuss and work through over the coming
years. And I think what people should have confidence in is that
we are deeply connected to this place.
Our name, Hereanuku, really speaks to the fact that
this whole process has been very much about the
restoration of whenua, the restoration of land, which we
hold dearly. Because there are some saying, "Oh, the trust will sell off
this land for millions of dollars," and all of these sorts of things, the
typical scaremongering.
But all we would say is that we are deeply tied and connected to these
places, and we will ensure that they are protected, not
only for this generation, but future generations. Thank you. Dr.
David Wilson, got a question there.
You're on mute, sir.
Thank you, Jamie, for that answer.
I think you may have actually answered my question.
You mentioned there are some things on the horizon, such as RMA, and
you did also mention changes of use that may be into the future.
So I think, in some ways, through the development of this bill,
there's some certainty there and some clarity there as to what
might happen post 25 years or in the
intervening years where we can work together.
I've seen many fabulous examples of that.
So hopefully, in the spirit of the conversation, that will
continue.
Most definitely, and I think it goes back to Karenza's comments earlier.
When this trust was established, and if you go back to the initial
terms of the trust and the principles that underpinned it, it was very
much to be an endowment for the benefit not only of the beneficiaries, but
actually for the region as a whole.
And we've been at pains to sort of just remind
the families and the wider community into
Taiihu
that this entity has a role to play in
contributing not only to our beneficiaries, but to the broader region.
And I think that's the piece that we're excited about, and I think it's
the piece that people shouldn't lose sight of.
It's interesting, we've had comments now of just sort of who have said, "Oh, we'd
prefer you to own and operate the park than others." But hey,
we're just sort of really happy that we've managed to sort of land in a place which
we think balances all interests and
gives certainty
Yeah, thanks, Jamie. Look, we have met time for your submission this morning, but
I think the committee really enjoyed hearing from you.
And certainly, we can see a real
joy that's beginning to come across as
we take this to the final stages, hopefully within the next couple of months.
So thanks again.
Kia ora, Dante.
Kia ora.
Members, we've now got the Indigenous Data Authority.
Lisa Pisoni, I believe, is joining us,
and as an organization has up to 10 minutes with
us.
Yep, are you there, Lisa?
Can you hear me?
Yes, we can. We're in your hands.
Oh, cool. For some reason I can't hear you. That's okay. All right.
Kia ora. Kia ora koutou. My name is Lisa Pisoni, and
I
am the founder and lead architect of the Indigenous Data Authority-
Lisa, your sound's coming through--
Lisa?
Which is-
... an Indigenous-owned, Māori-owned and led charitable trust that works
to operationalize Indigenous governance and practice.
Thank you for the opportunity to speak today.
First and foremost, I'd like to say that I support this bill.
To me, this bill is not simply about returning land.
It's about restoring authority.
The Nelson teens were never intended to be Crown land.
They were intended to remain under Māori ownership, with the Crown acting
as trustee. That promise has not been honored, and generations have
now lived-
Lisa?
... with those consequences. What this bill does-
... is quite significant because it recognizes that
distinction. It transfers legal title from Crown to former
trustee, as former trustee to Te Henui
Anuku Trust, while recognizing that beneficial
ownership has always remained with the
original customary owners, and creates a framework that
restores authority while recognizing that public conservation
management and public access will continue.
That distinction-
Lisa, can you hear? Lisa?
... is because governance and authority-
Lisa?
... are not the same thing.
Lisa? Lisa?
Sorry,
your sound's not very clear.
Oh, wait.
Your sound's not very clear.
Governance is how decisions are made, and
authority is who has the legitimate right to
make those decisions.
Chair, would Liam have her contact number and maybe give
her a call?
That
principle applies whether we are talking about Whenua Wai
Taonga data or artificial intelligence.
My professional work focuses on governance systems, and regardless of
the subject, the first question always needs to be the same.
Who has legitimate authority to decide?
To me, this bill begins to answer that question.
One of the strengths of this legislation is that it does not present
Māori authority and public administration as opposing
concepts. Instead, it creates a practical governance model where
both have a role to play. The Department of Conservation, local
authorities, and other public agencies will continue to have important
statutory responsibilities. At the same time, Te Henui
Anuku Trust will hold the legal authority of the
trustee on behalf of the beneficial owners.
That shouldn't be seen as a source of concern.
It should be recognized as an opportunity to strengthen governance.
For generations, Māori have exercised stewardship of these lands and waters
through whakapapa, tikanga, and intergenerational knowledge.
That knowledge has sustained these spaces long before modern
government agencies existed. Bringing that knowledge
together with the statutory responsibility of public institutions
creates a stronger foundation for decision-making
rather than the being able to make them
alone. Good governance is not about replacing one system with
another. It is about ensuring that every organization exercises
its responsibility within the limits of its
legitimate authority while working together in the interests of
both the whenua and the wider public,
which is also consistent with our constitutional foundations.
Article 2 of Te Tiriti o Waitangi guarantees the continued
exercise of tino rangatiratanga over lands, kaimoana, and
taonga. While this bill cannot undo generations of loss,
it recognizes that the authority over the whenua should sit with those
who hold enduring whakapapa connections to it.
It is equally consistent with the United Nations Declarations on the Rights of
Indigenous Peoples, which recognizes, of course, the rights of Indigenous
peoples to maintain and strengthen their relationship with their traditional lands,
territories, and resources and to maintain-
Liam, do we have an update on contacting Lisa?
These principles are increasingly recognized around the world because good
governance begins with legitimate authority.
My only recommendation is that this bill is implemented.
The authority of the beneficial owners remains central to
every decision made under it. Restoring legal title is
important. Restoring genuine decision-making authority is
essential. Finally, I hope Parliament sees this bill as more
than just a resolution of a historical grievance.
I hope it's recognized as a contemporary example of good
governance. When Parliament is considering Whenua
Wai, natural resources, data, artificial intelligence, or any other taonga,
the first question should never be, "How do we govern this?" The first question
should always be, "Who holds the legitimate authority?" Because
when authority sits with the right people, governance becomes legitimate.
And when authority is removed, governance becomes administrative.
That, to me, is what this bill begins to correct, and for that reason, I support
the bill. Ngā mihi nui
Kia ora, Lisa. Can you hear me okay? Can you hear me at all?
I can't hear you for some reason.
Can you take these out?
Can you hear me now through your computer?
Yeah. What about now?
Way better. Sorry. A lot of your presentation was a little bit distorted,
but we have got your-
Oh, was it?
We've got your written submission.
Okay.
And you're welcome to submit a further summary of what you spoke about.
But
I don't know if committee members have any key questions.
Probably just your last two sentences in summary would be really helpful, if you
could just repeat those.
So, basically it talks about
the question should never be, how do we govern this?
It should be, who holds legitimate authority?
And it should always go
to those people who whakapapa to the
whenua.
Because
when authority sits with the right people, governance becomes legitimate, and
when authority is removed, governance becomes administrative.
Yeah. Thank you.
And I think this bill addresses that.
Very good. We've got a question from Dr.
David Wilson, probably just-
Yes, I think
I got the gist that you're in favor of the bill,
with some,
should we say, some concerns.
But I missed the bit that you talked about in terms of AI.
Are you worried about data sovereignty there?
So it's about authority.
So obviously data sovereignty, sovereignty, governance,
it all ties together. It all fits together.
And part of what I do is I push for
indigenous authority.
And speaking to this, it's about the authority and the
legitimate authority of who should be making decisions or who
should be a part of the decision-making process.
And that's why I support this bill.
And can you relate what you just said to your point on AI
for me?
It's just given as an example. Because
even with AI, we as the
tangata whenua should have authority over anything
related to us. Yeah.
Thank you.
Okay. Thank you, Lisa. We have met time.
Appreciate your submission today.
Kia ora.
We're now going to go to Doug
and Maryanne from the Outdoor Access Commission.
Kia ora koutou.
Kia ora, Doug. We've got you for 10 minutes,
so we're in your hands. You're welcome to make some opening comments and then leave
some time for questions.
Kia ora. Tuatahi, e mihi ana ki te kaihanga, nana nei
ngā mea katoa.
Tuarua, ki a rātou katoa, ngā mātua tupuna kua wehe
atu ki te po, haere jure, haere e oki.
Tuatoru, ki a tātou katoa ngā kanohi ora.
Tuatahi ki te mana whenua o Te Tauihu, tēnā rawa atu
koutou i roto i tēnei kaupapa whakahirahira me
tēnei rā. Ki a koutou hoki, te komiti whakahaere o
tēnei wāhanga o te kaupapa, tēnā koutou, tēnā koutou.
Otirā, ki ngā tangata katoa o te whenua e
whakarongo ana ki ēnei kōrero, tēnā rawa atu
tātou katoa, Aotearoa whānui.
Here Anuku, the Outdoor Access Commission, is the Crown agent
responsible for public access to the
outdoors. We are established under the Walking Access
Act 2008, and our job is to advise
on and advocate for free, certain, enduring, and practical access on
foot, bike, horseback, or any other method for the many, many
purposes that we all enjoy as New Zealanders in
our beautiful country in the outdoors.
And we should note that we are all the public, regardless of
race, background, age, gender, origin.
And we should also note that public space
is a wonderful place where we all get to share
our cultures and being one another, including our mana
whenuatanga,
tanga,
for tangata whenua.
We have a national network of regional field advisors.
We map public access across the country and we're the agency people
and other agencies do and should come to when a change of land
affects how the public can move through it.
That is why a title transfer of this scale
sits squarely within our mandate.
The Commission supports the broad direction of the bill.
The Nelson Tents case is one of the longest running property
disputes in the history of Aotearoa,
and transferring and correcting legal title to Here
Anuku Trust as kaitiaki on behalf of owners is a
significant step for all of Aotearoa.
We also welcome the initial protections for public access and
recreation,
and we note that in our experience, mana whenua and
tangata whenua leadership in outdoor access
is most usually, if not always, a strength.
Correcting an ownership title of this scale will likely in
places mean a change to the public access
Both actual and potential. This is an expected
consequence of correcting the historic title, and it is
not in itself something that we oppose.
There are many examples where public access is actually
improved by unformed legal road stoppings, as one
example, whereby in those cases better alternatives are put in
place, or where ULRs were actually of no
relevance or interest to anybody.
The Outdoor Access Commission is taking a forward-looking stance
with relation to the bill moving forward.
Once the bill has passed and the title has transferred, we're
asking for the opportunity to sit down with Te Here Anuku
Trust,
for open blue skies without prejudice conversation and dialogue
about the future of public access.
We've found in our experience that outdoor access is best
managed and improved and enhanced when all parties think from
a blue skies approach, and we allow opportunities to
eventuate in a proactive relationship.
We're not asking the committee to change the bill.
We're asking it to note in its report support for this
engagement process to take place.
Please note that given the select committee time
frames, we haven't had the chance to analyze the unformed legal road
and land parcels involved for
their public access value, and
that is a gap.
Had we been brought into the conversation earlier, we could have provided useful
supportive background before the bill was drafted, not
to slow it down, but to help get the access settings right from the
start.
That's part of why we're asking to be part of the conversation moving
forward.
To sum up, we support the bill's broad direction.
We understand that some changes to practical access are expected as
part of the righting of this historic wrong,
and our one substantive ask is for the
committee's in-principle support for an
ongoing constructive relationship between
Te Here Anuku Trust and the Outdoor Access Commission.
Public access matters for connection to whenua for all,
for enriching our collective wairua as a country, and for improving
our biodiversity
and to the people who use it every day.
We want to keep being the voice that represents that interest and
be at the table.
Kia
ora.
Thank you, Doug. First question is from Dan Rosewarne.
Yeah, thanks Chair, and thanks Doug for that contribution.
You kind of half answered my question, but I just want to clarify.
So you mentioned around Clause 116 to stop
unformed legal roads, and noting that you haven't had a lot of
consideration time. I was just wondering, are there any particular examples
around these parcels of land that stick out for you that we should be
aware of?
I might defer to my colleague, Marianne, and just give a
quick general comment. When we look at unformed legal roads,
we look at both the current use, which sometimes is nothing,
sometimes is something, but also the future and potential use.
So it's quite an involved process, but I
hope Marianne is
here as well.
Yeah.
Kia ora, Marianne.
Kia ora, Doug.
Yeah, pretty much we haven't had time to fully analyze
all the particular parcels involved.
We note that some are actually mentioned in the
bill, then the schedules also have included
mention of other ones in Milnethorpe.
We're just conscious that even though vehicles mightn't
use these, the public still have the right to use them, and a lot
of the public do use them for walking and cycle ways.
And we're aware of a lot of projects for outdoor
access that are happening in the Golden Bay area in
particular that have identified unformed legal roads to get
off-road access for cycle ways and walking.
So we're just conscious that they
are included in the bill.
And yes, we'd like the ability to be able to have further
discussions involving any of those.
Thanks, Marianne.
Thank you. Steve Abel.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. Thank you Doug and
Marianne. I'm wondering, your key point is that
you'd like the opportunity to have that conversation with Te
Here Anuku.
I'm not sure if it's the committee's place to
intervene in that relationship, and I'm
concerned that
it seems that-- I presume you will have reached out to them already,
and that that is a matter between the Outdoor
Access Walking Trust and Te Here Anuku.
And I
wonder,
I'm not convinced that it's something for the committee to be making a comment on,
really.
I think it's implicit in the
assumption of the responsibility that Te Here Anuku has that
they
need to be the one that's approached as the authority holder.
Okay. If that is in fact the case, I think it's still been a fabulous
opportunity to express our stance
in terms of looking forward positively,
fully acknowledging the transfer and the correcting of the
title to the mana whenua,
and also acknowledging and putting forward the point that we are all
members of the public. Mana whenua, nga tangata katoa o
Aotearoa. But, uh, tena koe mo to-- mo tena
whakaaro.
Kia ora. And we absolutely admire the work you do, and no way questioning
the huge value of it and the essence of what you
represent as a principle of access.
So kia ora.
Kia ora, Steve.
Thank you, Doug, and for your organization and colleague online.
We have met time,
so appreciate your submission today.
Kia ora.
Thank you.
Members, we're going to go to Dr. Lorraine Eade,
who's making a personal submission.
Are you there, Dr. Lorraine?
Kia ora. Kia ora. Can you hear me?
Kia ora. Yes. We've only got you for five minutes, so I encourage you to largely
take your submission as read to allow time for questions.
Ka pai. So first of all, I just want to acknowledge Uncle Pat,
Uncle Rory Stafford, for over 40 years of leadership
around Y56 and this private law case.
That's a heavy load for anyone to carry, so just want to acknowledge
and honor
him.
Just in terms of the Spain Award, of the 151,000 odd
acres, 69,000
entitlement of those acres were set for Ngati Rarua
and Takaka, Mutapi, Mutuika, and Motiri.
So that 69,000 acres equates to just
45.746%.
The crux of my submission is around the
decision
of August 2023 to allow other uri,
other iwi,
into the Nelson tents case. So there were
254 tupuna that were listed in the
original Native Land Court hearing.
Now, in terms of that, they followed due process through the Native Land Court,
and Ngati Rarua, Te Atiawa, Ngati Tama, and Ngati Koata
were identified as owners of the Nelson tents.
A decision was made overnight to include other
tupuna without coming back to the descendants of
those original 254 tupuna.
That's basically the crux
of the submission. It's another injustice on top of
injustice over the last 181 years.
In terms of the lands, the treaty settlement process
that we've gone through,
Ngati Rarua also included the Nelson tents in their claim,
and this seems like an injustice to Ngati Rarua,
who had the majority of land share ownings,
and now we have other owners in there.
One of the things that we would like to see, and you
can see there's some signatories in there.
Just for your information, Eru Kipa has
withdrawn his signature
from the petition. He didn't quite read it 100%, so
he has withdrawn. So there's 19 people who
have supported the submission
as to go through the Maori Land Court process in terms of
determining who are the customary owners
of those lands. Now, we have been
through a number of processes,
and signaled this at AGMs, at Te Hiri Nuku
open
hui, and we've got nowhere, really.
So this is predominantly the last opportunity
to have it on record. No matter what happens, at
least I can tell my mokopuna when they come to
challenge in two generations' time,
that this was put forward. So kia ora.
I think I've got a minute left.
You have.
Yeah. Thank you for your submission.
Obviously, you stood up and shared these concerns during the process
with Te Hiri Nuku.
What was their response to some of your concerns?
That it was an overnight decision.
It was at the remedies hearing.
Evidence was going to be given the next day, and advice was
provided. They were between a rock and a hard place.
Advice was provided,
and an agreement was made. Now, we've never seen that agreement,
but obviously there are another tupuna, there are other owners in Te
Hiri Nuku. And just in terms of equity and justice,
think that that needs to go back through the Maori Land Court,
who determined who the original owners
were in 1892.
Very good. All right. Well, we-
So we've not got very far, is what I'm saying.
Thank you. Appreciate your submission, and you certainly discharged your
obligations to do everything in your power.
So acknowledge the work you've done there.
Kia ora.
Kia ora. Members, we're now going to welcome Dr. Nick Smith.
This is also in a personal capacity
Dr Nick, are you there?
I indeed am. Kia ora to yourself, Ryan, and
to members of the Select
Committee. Really appreciate the opportunity to be able to make a
submission. This is a hugely significant bill for the
Nelson and Tasman communities, and my submission is
particularly focused on one of our gems, the Abel
Tasman National Park. There has not been the time for either
of our councils, with the list of properties affected only becoming
public a bit over a week ago, for our councils to make submissions,
so this is in my own role individually, albeit I note
over 1,800 people have signed a petition with similar concerns to
mine with respect to the Abel Tasman National Park.
I emphasize that I do not question the need to
resolve the Nelson tents issue. My concern
is that we are not going to get the best outcome for our region
or for the new Te Hārihi Nuku Trust and its beneficial owners due
to the rushed process and the lack of community engagement,
both on the deed and this bill.
The big picture is we inherit the
consequences of both good and bad decisions of
our predecessors.
180 years ago, the New Zealand Company,
Nelson settlers, and the Crown did a horrible
wrong in not honoring the Nelson tents.
But the decision 80 years ago to create the Abel Tasman
National Park and protect it in perpetuity
was a superb decision.
My worry with this bill is that in trying to fix
the bad of that 1840s failure over
the tents, that we undermine that
decision of huge wisdom in creating the Abel Tasman National
Park.
Now, the fundamental purpose
of a national park, whether in New Zealand or abroad,
is that it's protected in perpetuity for nature's sake.
This bill removes that permanent
protection over the most significant portion
of the Abel Tasman National Park, which is 1,600
hectares of its coast.
This is the most
significant diminution
of national park protection
in over a century in our country's
history, and it's on New Zealand's smallest
and most popular national park. Now, whether it's Clause
28 that allows areas of that 1,600 hectares to be
removed before the 25-year review of the license,
or the absolute discretion of the trust to end the coverage
of the National Parks Act, and its protections
from 2051.
Now, this is not to question for a moment the integrity of the good people on the
trust. My problem is the removal of the
National Parks Act's protections, and we need to
recognize that the new private trust will have a very
different set of accountabilities as to those of a government
department or a council.
Now, it's incredibly noteworthy
that the Crown excluded from the deed areas like
state highways that it said were strategically too important to
be transferred to the trust.
Yet when it came to the areas of the Abel Tasman, it took a different
approach.
Secondly, there is absolutely no requirement
in the decision of the courts over the tents to
remove the permanent protection of the National Parks Act.
That is being done by Parliament and not the courts, and there are
significant areas, including areas I was involved with from my time as
minister, like the Lords River, in Stewart
Island, Rakiura, where the National Parks
Act remains over private land. I'd also draw to the
Select Committee's attention the far more imaginative and better
solutions for areas like the Two Ureweras and Mount
Taranaki,
where we have been able to come up with a co-governance
model that appropriately recognizes Maori ownership while keeping those
protections. I would be very supportive of a
model whereby all 22,000 hectares of the
Abel Tasman National Park was held in joint
Crown-Trust title, but the protections of the National
Parks Act were retained in perpetuity.
Dr Nick-
There are dozens of reserves across Nelson and Tasman that are
affected by this. There hasn't been the chance to make a submission.
My number one plea is rushed law is too often
flawed law, and be very aware of what you are doing.
Do you wish your grandchildren to be able to enjoy, as
this generation has, the free access and the nature
of the Abel Tasman National Park? Because that is what is at
question with this bill.
Thank you, Dr Nick. A very clear submission.
We have run out of time for questions, of course, but
I don't think you've left any questions as to your position on it, so thank you
for your time this morning.
We're now going to move to Gillian Rattray.
Gillian, are you there?
This is also in a personal capacity.
Tena koutou katoa. Can you hear me all right?
Have you got a video?
Can hear you all right. Have you got a video you can turn on for us, Gillian?
Oh, yes. My apologies.
Fantastic. We've got five minutes with you.
I encourage you to leave some time for questions.
Thank you. Tena koutou katoa. Thank you for the opportunity
to speak to my submission
I am not, in my submission, asking the committee to revisit the settlement
that resolves a long-standing historical injustice by
restoring the legal ownership of the Nelson Tenths lands to Te
Heri Anuku Trust. My submission asks a different
question: how can this legislation leave the best
possible legacy for future generations?
My comments and recommendations focus particularly on the land that will become
Te Heri Anuku National Park land.
By way of background, I grew up in Motueka, and my family
has lived in the Nelson region since 1842.
While this is a personal submission, I have chaired the board of
Project Janszoon for the past 10 years.
Project Janszoon has invested over 21 million in restoring
the ecological health of Abel Tasman National Park,
working alongside the Department of Conservation, mana whenua, local
communities, and scientists.
Over the past decade, I have seen it firsthand what a long-term partnership,
backed with significant funding, can achieve at a landscape scale.
We've seen native birds return. We've seen ecosystems recover.
We've learnt that restoration is not something that is ever finished.
It requires commitment over generations.
That experience has shaped the perspective I bring to this bill.
The opportunity created by this legislation is much bigger than a
transfer of legal title. It is an opportunity to
demonstrate that restoring ownership and restoring the whenua are
complementary aspirations.
The bill contains important mechanisms that continue conservation management and
maintain continuity for Abel Tasman National Park.
I support these provisions, but they need to continue beyond the
25-year license period in perpetuity, as
is a basic principle for our national parks.
Clause 23 clearly states that Te Heri Anuku National
Park land is a national park and forms part
of Abel Tasman National Park.
My recommendations, detailed in my written submission, seek
to strengthen the stewardship framework around these provisions.
In particular, I encourage the committee to consider recognizing more
explicitly that the management of these lands should aim not only
to maintain their values, but to progressively enhance them.
This means protecting biodiversity, restoring ecosystems,
learning through science and monitoring, working in partnership, and
leaving the land in better condition for those who come after us.
I strongly support the review provided in Clause 47 of the bill.
I encourage the committee to ensure that this review looks not only at whether the
legal arrangements are working, but whether the whenua itself
is healthier.
In my view, that is how the long-term success of this legislation should be
judged. The true legacy of this bill will not simply
be that legal ownership has been restored.
It will be whether decades from now people can look back
and say that this parliament restored ownership while also creating,
with the Te Heri Anuku Trust,
the conditions for the continued ecological and cultural
restoration of these remarkable lands and the
opportunity for all New Zealanders and
visitors to enjoy them.
Yeah. Thank you.
That would be a legacy worthy of both the history that
this bill addresses and the generations that will follow us. Thank you.
Thank- thanks, Gillian. I'll go to Steve, because you missed out last time.
We've only got about 30 seconds, uh, left for question and answer.
Gillian, isn't the issue that the Crown never had the authority to
put the land into national park? Even though that was
a wonderfully good thing to do with the land under the belief that the Crown had
that authority. What the court has found and what this bill restores
is the authority of the true owners, being Te Heri
Anuku. And if we
maintain perpetuity
obligation on that private land now,
then it's not a true restoration of the injustice.
I'm not a lawyer. And in terms of
those legal questions, my concern is just that this
is, as
Nick Smith has expressed, this is an extremely
important part of our national park heritage, and my
concern is that
in perpetuity it is there as a valued and
improved
piece of our heritage, my heritage, everybody's
heritage.
Thanks, Gillian.
And I would also point out the significant investment that has gone into that park
in recent years from a philanthropic fund.
Yeah. Thank you, Gillian-
Good on them
... for that submission and obviously for your work in this part of
New Zealand. Fantastic.
Thank you, Mr. Chair.
We're now going to go to Craig Atkinson.
Kia ora.
Kia ora, Craig.
Good to see you all again.
We've got you for five minutes.
You're ahead.
Yeah, well, I think this is the move in the right direction, and it
should be celebrated by all New Zealanders across the
country. And I think this sets a precedent for the
treaty claims going forward,
of what is actually what I speak about as a main cause and not the
appetizer that's given out. And I think
I have no concerns at all of Maori protecting
the lands and stuff.
For the last 10 years that I have engaged with them from the
treaty grounds up at Waitangi, I was sent to stand
under the treaty Under the flag and discuss
the future of New Zealand with one of the leaders from the lower
marae, that I've traveled around to the treaty claims for the last seven
years, and I've only ever been welcome with aroha from all Maori.
I look at Maori as one, and always have.
On Monday at the marae, it was described to me by
the Honorable
Adrian Rata that Maori
could struggle in certain areas to connect as one.
But I think this legislation sets a precedence for all
Maori to fill the waka and sail in one direction, and
actually for the Crown to return all the land that he stole
from. And I think this is
legislation that puts a precedence that we can return
Maori land to-
Right
... across the country. So thank you for my time.
No problem.
Any questions?
No questions?
Doesn't appear to be any questions, Craig.
Your submission was obviously very succinct though, so thank you for that.
Thank you. Kia ora.
Thank you, Craig. Kia ora.
Have we got Mr Arthur Phillips
ready to go?
Yes.
Can see you there, Arthur. Just need to unmute and turn your video
on.
Fantastic.
Ka pai.
Ka pai. We've got you for five minutes, sir. So in your hands.
Feel free to save some time for questions.
Okay. Kia ora tātou, Members of Parliament.
Salutations to each of you. Ko Arthur Phillips taku ingoa.
I am not a lawyer, but I was a researcher for my Ngati Raru people that
led to the deeds of settlement between Ngati Raru and the Crown.
I spent 20 years in the role before moving on.
I'm an uri of original Ngati Raru owners in the Nelson
Tenants, now known as Wakatu Incorporation.
My submission is in opposition to the Te Heri and Nuku
Nelson Tenants Bill. I believe it has been rushed with little
consultation, lack of consent, and authorization.
I draw your attention to index three within my submission.
It is a copy of the Nelson Maori Land Court Minute book 3,
1892 to 1899. It defines the
four iwi who made up who we now know as the iwi of the
Nelson Tenants, Wakatu. They were Ngati Raru, Ngati Ava, Ngati
Tama, and Ngati Koata. It is historical, evidential
fact by the court made to all parties involved in the court decision.
I note that Rangitane are speaking today.
I believe further research is required
on their 26 named people
within the original tupuna list. Was it through marriage, state of
subjection, or Commissioner Spain allocating land to those
working the land for
the rangatira within the forenamed iwi recognized through Raupatu?
I believe this research needs to happen before the bill is passed, as it could
open the doors, sadly, on further grievances.
I also believe it will have a detrimental effect on the
deed of settlement Ngati Raru has signed with the Honorable
Chris Finlayson as Attorney General in 2013,
if follow-up research is not undertaken by the Crown before the bill
is passed. The majority of land Crown wants to gift falls
within the rohe of Ngati Raru. It will become another
disassociation from our cultural lands.
Of the 151,000 acres which made up the tenants,
69,000 acres came under
the mana, the mantle, of Ngati Raru.
This makes up 45.7% of the total. Now,
our traditional fishing village at Manuka Island at the southern end of the boulder
bank of Nelson, this bill gives it away to an independent body that
has had little contact with me as an uri of the
original Ngati Raru tupuna on what are now becoming gift lands.
As in my brief in index one, the bill is giving away
kakā at Kaiteriteri, an important cultural site for not
only Ngati Raru, but also two other iwi involved in the
Raupatu. The bill is giving away our cultural areas,
our traditional foreshores within our 69,000 acre area.
Further research needs to take place on every area to be gifted to show
the importance of each site. As you can identify through the
profiles from the Te Heri and Nuku establishment team, it
notes their whakapapa and the relationship through marriages
at interlinks within the different tribes.
Through this, and with some trustees having key positions within the
recognized iwi and Wakatu itself, their fiduciary duty
could be compromised through the rushing of the bill through Parliament and the
negative impact this could create.
Ngati Raru has always said we only want what is rightfully ours.
Nothing more, nothing less. If this becomes a further
grievance in the future, then instead of the
3% of the true value we received at our settlement,
then we believe, I believe, Ngati Raru should
push for the full 97% still owed.
I was also an intervener witness in the early High Court case,
Rory Stafford versus Crown for Ngati Raru, as we needed our story
placed on record.
I would like to thank Liam Perkins for his support in this process as well.
Kia
ora.
Kia ora. Thank you, Arthur, for your submission.
We have got one question from Steve Abel.
Kia ora, Arthur. Thank you for your submission.
Um
Broadly,
just for clarity, you're concerned that the overlapping
interests in the area and the Ngati
Rauru interest is not taken account of, and that this might
have the effect of extinguishing
your right to make a
claim to that interest and
that association?
Yes.
So I wonder if--
I think we as a committee to seek some advice on this in terms of
the impact it has on other
groups in the same rohe that are covered by this bill.
And I think your submission makes it very clear what your concerns
are, and I, for one, will be seeking some advice from officials on that.
Thank you.
Kia ora.
Okay. Thank you, Arthur, for your submission. We have met time.
Appreciate you coming in today.
Kia ora. Thank you for the time.
Kia ora.
We're now going to move to the William Stafford Trust.
This is an organizational submission,
which we have for up to 10 minutes.
Joseph Stafford, I believe, is presenting.
Yeah, I can see you, Joe. Kia ora. Welcome.
Kia ora.
We're in your hands. Obviously, recommend you leave some time for questions at the
end of your submission.
Sure.
At marii koutou katoa.
E Zoom hui mai nei. He mihi mahana ki a koutou kua tae
mai nei i tenei wa. Tena koutou. Ko wai
au? Ko Joe Stafford toku ingoa. Ko Ngati Rauru raua ko Ngati Tama
oku iwi. Ko Te Tauihu, ko Wairau
toku turanga waewae.
Thank you for this opportunity to be heard on this bill this morning.
My name is Joe Stafford, father to Case and Milan Stafford, son to
Wiremu Tapate Stafford, and brother to Terehia Nadia Dean Stafford, and
uncle to their many children and grandchildren.
Along with my brother and sister-in-law, Steve Marshall and Kiri, respectively,
we are the trustees and/or beneficiaries of the William Stafford Trust,
customary owners of Wakatu Incorporation, owner number
75882.
We whakapapa to those very lands that sit within this bill.
Now, my father, Wiremu Stafford, along with his brother Kupa, Uncle Kupa, and a few
others, were central to the establishment of the Wakatu Incorporation in
1977. When you Google when was the incorporation established, it
returns, I quote, "Was officially established by an Order in
Council August 4, 1977, formed by descendants
of customary Maori landowners to take over management of their
ancestral lands, known as the Nelson Tents Reserves".
These descendants of the customary Maori landowners were, in fact,
my dad and my uncle and a few other uncles that have passed away.
So have
a very, very deep vested interest in this case.
I just want to make the point, too, that their decision
to include our whanau lands into the collective of Wakatu
was a demonstration on their part to self-determine a future for the many by the
few.
Also,
I, as well my siblings, we know
very well those lands in Motueka and Nelson that are tupuna owned,
that were passed into the greater collective of Wakatu Incorporation.
We know these lands. We have walked them, dug them, played rugby on them,
eaten the apples and the kiwifruit from them.
We understand acutely the loss of cultural and spiritual connection as
individuals, as a whanau from these lands, but we understood the need and
benefit for these lands to sit within a much larger collective, being the Wakatu
Incorporation.
We, along with many owners of Wakatu, have been heavily engaged over the last
50 years in the running and governance of Wakatu.
My brother-in-law, Steve Marshall, was chair for two decades.
My sister, Terehia, was a board member for three terms.
So our identity as a whanau can only be described as mutually
inclusive with these very lands and with Wakatu Incorporation.
Now, that said,
you can hopefully appreciate the gravity of significance impacting not just us,
but all owners of Wakatu when I say at no time during the Nelson Tents
claim were we, the owners, ever consulted with as
owners of Wakatu, the very people and funders, I might add, too,
to the claim,
that our Wakatu committee reps should have been taking their instruction
from. Consultation with us as owners was lumped together with
non-owners and iwi interested parties.
Secondly, and probably most critical, my cousin, Rory
Stafford,
at no stage never consulted with the customary owners of his
decision to include Ngati Apa into our Nelson Tents claim.
He, as well the other Wakatu representatives, had not only a fiduciary
duty to consult with the owners, but also a tikanga responsibility to
do so.
And to add to this, our Wakatu chair and deputy chair, who were
pressuring Rory to include Ngati Apa, had a direct and
undisclosed conflict of interest to us, the owners, in that they were Ngati Apa.
Look, so this is all I will say this morning, given the time.
My submission speaks in more detail to the remedy we seek.
I thank you for the opportunity to speak and represent my whanau, my siblings, and
my dad and his brother. No reira, tena koutou, tena koutou,
tena rā koutou katoa.
Kia ora. Thank you for your submission, Joe.
We have a question from Steve Abel.
Kia ora, Steve.
Yeah. Kia ora, Joe. And it's not so much a question, because I think your
position is very clear. It's more that-
I'll be seeking advice from officials on
the substance of the point you're making and
whether there's a risk to
extinguishment of a
customary or treaty right through the process of this bill, and how
that might be addressed.
I could add, Steve, too, that I, crikey, what would've been over the last
three months,
I've sent a letter to the Maori Land Court,
I'm happy to furnish this to you guys as well,
asking them for guidance on what
steps are available to us when
their processes
aren't being followed or haven't been followed.
And I
got a letter back to say they've received--
Sorry, an email back to say that they've received my letter, but no
formal response.
Okay. That's useful to know. Yeah, if you're happy to share that then that
perhaps could assist us.
Okay. How do I do that?
Just email the committee address, I guess, Ryan, is that right?
Yeah. Through the clerk of the committee. Yeah.
No problem. Easy.
Okay.
Thank you, Joseph. That appears to be the end of our questioning.
Thank you for your submission. Very comprehensive.
Thank you.
Kia ora. Thank you, Joseph.
Bye.
Okay. Have we got Louise ready to go? We're a few minutes ahead.
Sorry,
Mr. Chair. Louise has pulled out, so we've got Te Tiriti o
Waitangi Marae next.
Okay, and they're ready to go?
Just bringing them in now.
Oh, fantastic.
Sorry, you did tell me that.
Ngati
Kawa taitua, welcome.
Mōrena.
We've got you for 10 minutes. We're in your hands.
Kia koutou katoa. Ngati Kawa tene.
Mi Hana kia koutou. Yeah, thanks for
the time to
present my oral submission.
Can I just ask a question?
Sure.
I'm not aware of who's on the panel today.
Can you just quickly-
Yeah, sure. You've got myself as chair, Ryan Hamilton, Dan
Bidois, Nancy Lu,
and Paolo Garcia, and Todd
Stevenson, Dr. David Wilson,
Dr. Deborah Russell, Rachel Boyack, Steve
Abel, and am I missing anyone?
I think that's all of us. So it's, yeah.
Dan Rosewarne.
Oh, Dan Rosewarne. Apologies, Dan.
Oh, kia ora. Thank you for that. Oh, greetings, everyone. Mōrena.
Yeah, so first of all,
just want to celebrate Rory Stafford and the Waka Tu Inc
getting this far with the bill.
As I mentioned, I'm in support,
with some conditions and
hopefully some amendments to the bill
to improve the position.
Yeah, I'm the chairman of Te Tiriti o Waitangi Marae.
So I was born and raised here in the north, Whangarei, Ngapuhi.
And yeah, coming from the
perspective that
the fiduciary
duty
and the equity
was granted by my tupuna
in 1835 and 1840.
So the Crown has
to comply with their fiduciary duties with
international
law and global financing.
Yeah. They
obviously have to follow
tikanga and customs of our Maori nation.
So yeah, in my submission, I've provided some
advice
to Te Herenga Waka Trust
in regards to the customary unextinguished native title.
Yeah. And so that's,
I guess, the core of my submission.
Yeah, so I just wanted to present that
orally to you today. So
just want to keep it brief. I know I got 10 minutes, but I thought I'd leave it
open for some questions.
Yeah. Thank you. You've got quite a comprehensive submission there.
And obviously you were largely supportive of the bill as it
stands.
Yeah. I guess
it covers
quite a few things in there, but I guess
my main point in the submission is that the Crown
has made a confession that they didn't own
the land, and they were a trustee
and-
That's pretty much
what it says in the bill. So it's clear
that they have
kind of ceded
in the bill,
and there's evidence of that in there.
Thank you. Steve Abel.
Kia ora.
Sorry, I had my mute on.
I
sense that you're proposing that in a broader sense than just the
specific tenths agreements. But are you also
alluding to the other tenths agreements there are
around the country, and I know there are in the north,
that this sets a precedent for the Crown's
obligations to
recognize that where those tenths agreements were not fulfilled,
the Crown is acting as a trustee and should return
at least that
10% that was guaranteed in those agreements?
I guess
the breach is actually the fact that
the trustees haven't
distributed the equity to the beneficiaries,
and that's since 1840,
so it's a long-standing issue.
So yeah.
The bill kind of doesn't
hit that point.
But yeah, that's why I'm
putting forward that there should be some amendments.
And what should the amendments be, do you think?
So yeah, I guess the red flag
is that
they're shifting away from the Maori Land Court jurisdiction
and placing the trust under the High Court,
as a
trust outside the Maori Land Court's jurisdiction.
So yeah.
Putting forward the amendment that they should,
yeah, do the Maori Land Court.
Okay.
Yep.
That's clear. Thank you.
Okay. Well, thank you for your submission.
It appears that we've reached the end of questions as well from members,
so acknowledge your submission today, and thank you
for coming along.
Kia ora. Ngā mihi.
Kia ora.
Liam, have we got--
Yep. Rewa Morgan, Whanau Trust.
And then I think members after this, we're having a short break.
Kia ora, good morning.
Morena koutou, Chair.
Tena koutou to the Select Committee.
Paul Morgan's my name, and you've received my submission.
I did leave a brief context intro to my
name,
and basically, I've been involved with Maori
land matters in Taiahu, the Nelson tenths,
for most of my life, 50 years.
In terms of
the claims,
I was Wakatu Incorporation committee member for
35 years, chairman for 20 plus.
I have been deeply involved in the
Waitangi Tribunal and
High Court,
Court of Appeal, Supreme Court process.
Just to give you context in terms of whakapapa whenua and history,
I acted as the
expert witness for Wakatu and my own people of
Ngati Rarua through those years, and particularly
in 2010 in the High Court when we established
the historical facts of the New Zealand
tenths-- Sorry, the Nelson tenths case.
My submission is focusing on a number
of points. As I've said in there, the trust,
we submit an opposition to a number of key elements, and
it's important for me to give you further context.
This bill as it's written
and the way it's structured,
in my view,
won't
last the time in the sense that
for the tangata whenua and for particularly Ngati Rarua,
as you've heard from the submission of Dr.
Lorraine, which I'm a signatory to that,
there's some fundamental issues in the bill
that need addressing.
There was a comment about governance, and at the heart of this,
who are the governors? Are they the people with authority,
the customary owners?
Or is the governance that you've got in this bill just an administrative
one?
That's a very important point for reflection
because
in my work, my lifelong work, and I've been into the parliament
many times on many bills,
we've always focused on
sustainability of what is being created
and whether it will fulfill its purpose.
And I'm of the view that this bill won't do that at
this point in time.
When you look at our concerns,
we've expressed the issue about the submission process,
and I'd have to say for a person that's been involved-
With this claim, the Nelson tense for 50 years,
and the fact it's outstanding matter for 181 years, the
timeframe and the process being provided by
the parliament, the select committee process,
has put us all under significant
stress and difficulty in trying to participate in a process that's
been going on this long. And personally,
my belief is that the select committee
should have fronted on the marae of Te Tauihu so you really
deeply understand the implications of what you will be
recommending.
The process since
2022,
and it's important they differentiate between Wakatu Incorporation, the committee
of management, WI 56,
and then the transition across to Te Herenuku, and that
transition was a poor one. I say poor because
the owners
of Wakatu, the shareholders of Wakatu, and other customary owners
didn't really have an informed
debate to the process and the
milestones looking to be achieved,
and there was no mandate approval given to the parties.
So we're quite clear on that, as
that's been poor.
In terms of
the submission, we've spoken of the process and timeframe, the
mandate.
A key issue obviously in this bill is what the
governance structure's going to be.
It was our early, certainly my early
advocacy that we put together a discussion
paper on the options
for the trust's
settlement, and I'm talking about legal entities.
And the select committee should be mindful that
in our region, we've a lot of experience on that.
Wakatu Incorporation
was formed in the 1970s through the Royal Commission and Reserve
Lands Commission of Inquiry.
That was put to vote by the owners.
Completely different process to this,
a
hui
mandated process and a final vote.
And through that process you get ownership of the
beneficiaries, the shareholders, the owners, and that's not what
is happening here, and you should be clear on that.
The governance structure, you've heard that Ngati Rauru has
45.7% of the estate.
We expect the materiality of our ownership
to be reflected in the governance,
and we expect our ownership to be acknowledged.
We have through the 1993 Ngati
Rauru
Iwi Empowering Bill and Act
1993,
we put some of those clear governance conditions and
benchmarks into that bill
on the receiving back of the lands from the Anglican Church
that were taken under Governor Grey's
direction in 1853.
I'm saying this because we're experienced in the transfer of
assets,
and it's important that you clearly
consider the governance structure,
how the beneficiaries, owners will engage with the
trustees, and actually where the authority lies.
This bill
is essentially saying the trustees have unfettered
power
in terms of governance decisions.
I say that because in my submission,
the land will transfer back as general land,
not as Maori freehold land, and you should
closely consider this because Maori freehold land
is subject to Te Ture Whenua Maori
1993.
Under the Land Act,
there is a governance operating
system under the law
which recognizes the owners, the beneficiaries'
authority,
and this bill does not deliver that.
I would say,
and I didn't necessarily want to bring it up,
but the issues that some of the public, including
the Honorable Nick Smith are bringing up,
because it's general land and it's unfettered,
there is a risk around the alienation process.
So,
I'm fully aware of that. We have policies, we have law, we have
processes so that the owners, the
beneficiaries may or may not determine those types of
decisions, and this bill doesn't meet those
obligations.
We've talked about the trust structure in my submission.
We've discussed the Maori land jurisdiction,
and the next issue is the issue of Nga Uri,
the beneficiaries.
Thanks, Paul. I'm just mindful of time-
Yeah
... sir. Do you want to maybe say some closing comments?
I know we've got a question from Dr. David Wilson.
Okay. If you've got some questions, that's fine.
There's a general
comment that people are excited about where we're at.
We've made great progress
enormous progress to get to here. My advocacy to the select
committee is do the job properly so that we have a
sustainable bill and act that meets the
needs of the beneficiaries, the owners, into the future.
Thank you. Dr David Wilson.
Tenā koe, Paul. That's a very good submission. Thank you for that.
I picked up that some of the key issues here,
two main ones, where authority lies, but also the governance structure.
Could you talk to us about that, and subsequent to that, have you spoken
to the Māori Land Trustee?
Well, at the moment, these transitional trustees, there's 14 of them.
They weren't appointed by the owners, so there will obviously need to be a
process to appoint trustees, and how
many, well, that will need to be determined.
The
governance, they're promoting a Whakapapa register
of one person, one vote. But we've got to understand that
the trust assets are owned by beneficiaries and
owners,
and they have an ownership stake in those lands.
We use the trust terminology because we took this legal case on that basis,
but underpinning this, we are customary land owners.
We are the owners of the land,
and it needs to be structured to respect the
authority of the owners.
Thank you, Paul.
Thank you, Paul. A very clear submission, and your input
will help consolidate the select committee's
final consideration. So I appreciate your submission today and the work you're
doing.
Kia ora. Thank you all very much.
Kia ora.
Liam, for some reason I can't type in the chat, but
we are scheduled for a break now. Do you want us to stick to the
timing for the other submitters coming in, so from 10:00 till
10:25, or do you want to bring it forward a little bit?
Are you able to bring it forward a little bit?
It might be difficult to bring all of the submitters forward just because it would
create a gap later on, so probably best to stick to 10:25.
Okay, members, got a decent break, so we'll see you back 10:25.
Thank you.
Thanks, guys.